<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="schemas/wf-examples.sch" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<wf-examples>
   <!-- This XML file is populated with a variety of WF URIs. The structure of the XML file is evolving, so 
   there is no schema yet. The schematron file pointed to above does some basic checks. Most important, it is
   used to test the function wf:parse-wf-uri() against the examples below. -->
   
   <!-- This document begins with two major sections, one on scriptum types and another on work types, and 
   thinks about these categories in terms of reference system traditions. After that come the examples. -->

   <scriptum-types>
      <!-- Scriptum types below are diagnostic, not exhaustive categories. They are chosen based not
         upon a pure taxonomy of scripta but upon the types of reference systems traditions that have 
         developed over time. Because these are scripta, the reference systems endemic to them are
         material. Items are ordered from most specific to least specific, with the understanding that
         when checking for the rules for a particular scriptum, the user should work with the first
         category that seems appropriate.
      -->
      <!-- WF-support takes values: excellent, good, mixed, poor, and none. The values provide a guess
      as to what percentage of scripta of the given type can be the target of WF URIs. -->
      <!-- Ref-system types declare the types reference systems supported by WF syntax. In a given
         <ref-system> the <step>s are ordered. If the base URI points to a particular step,
         then the reference system commences with the next <step> in the process.
      -->
      <scriptum-type xml:id="papyrus">
         <name>papyrus</name>
         <wf-support>mixed</wf-support>
         <desc>A reed-based type of paper used for writing in the ancient world. It tends to survive
            only fragmentarily. Reference systems are supported primarily through the checklist
            supplied at http://papyrus.info. Bear in mind that the reference system begins with the
            first step that can be converted to a digit. If part of a multivolume effort to publish
            a collection of papyri, this will begin with a volume number, but not necessarily so.
            Above all, remember that this scriptum type applies only when the primary scriptum in
            question is the papyrus, not a replication of it (book, online). If the primary scriptum
            is a replication, look further in this list for an appropriate category. </desc>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <base-uri-source>https://papyri.info</base-uri-source>
            <base-uri-source>https://trismegistos.org</base-uri-source>
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <ref-systems>
            <desc>Papyrus collections are well curated, with unique numbers assigned to a group of
               papyri that might be long with each other. Some papyri accumulate multiple URIs based
               on the collections that have itemized them. The base URI is normally built to point
               to the papyrus through a publication, its volume, and then a catalog number. Once
               that base URI is in place, all that is left is identifying the line in question.
               However, this applies only when one is pointing to the papyrus itsewf, and not to an
               edition of a papyrus. If an WF URI is intended to be made about a particular edition,
               see below, under journal or book, and examples.</desc>
            <!-- This could use input from Mark DePauw et al. -->
            <ref-system type="material">
               <step>line</step>
               <!-- How do they handle column - line interaction? -->
            </ref-system>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>

      <scriptum-type xml:id="ostracon">
         <name>ostracon</name>
         <wf-support>mixed</wf-support>
         <desc>Pottery, normally broken in shards, used for writing. Principles laid down for papyri
            apply here as well.</desc>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <base-uri-source>https://papyri.info</base-uri-source>
            <base-uri-source>https://trismegistos.org</base-uri-source>
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <ref-systems>
            <desc>Ostraca are treated much like papyri, but finding base URIs are generally harder
               than with papyri. Remember, if the target scriptum is the ostracon itsewf, the base
               uri should not point to a modern publication.</desc>
            <xref target="papyrus"/>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>

      <scriptum-type xml:id="inscription">
         <name>inscription</name>
         <wf-support>mixed</wf-support>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <base-uri-source>https://www.eagle-network.eu/</base-uri-source>
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <desc>An object in a hard medium where text has been carved, chiseled, engraved, or
            embossed into the base material. Includes portable and nonportable items, e.g., coins,
            seals, lintels, arches, walls, columns, stones, clay.</desc>
         <ref-systems>
            <xref target="papyrus"/>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>
      
      <scriptum-type xml:id="journal">
         <name>journal</name>
         <wf-support>excellent</wf-support>
         <desc>A scriptum that is intended to have installments be published at intervals (weekly,
            monthly, quarterly, annually), and without plans for termination. Includes magazines,
            newsletters. Does not include newspapers, which may need special treatment in WF.</desc>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <base-uri-source></base-uri-source>
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <ref-systems>
            <ref-system type="material">
               <step>volume</step>
               <step optional="true">issue</step>
               <step>page</step>
               <step type="implicit">line</step>
            </ref-system>
            <ref-system type="material">
               <step>volume</step>
               <step optional="true">issue</step>
               <step>page</step>
               <step>note</step>
               <step type="implicit">line</step>
            </ref-system>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>
      
      <scriptum-type xml:id="newspaper">
         <name>newspaper</name>
         <wf-support>good</wf-support>
         <desc>A periodical that is published daily or on a frequent basis, and intended to present
            readers with reports and commentary on recent events.</desc>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <base-uri-source></base-uri-source>
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <ref-systems>
            <ref-system type="material">
               <step optional="true">volume</step>
               <step optional="true">issue</step>
               <step optional="true">section</step>
               <step>page</step>
               <step>block</step>
               <step>column</step>
               <step type="implicit">line</step>
               <comment>A section label must lend itsewf to a type of ordering system that can be
                  converted to numerals. If a newspaper's ordered sections draw from the Latin
                  alphabet, but there are gaps, then the sequence should be converted into
                  consecutive integers starting with 1. For example, a newspaper issue with sections
                  labeled A, B, C, S (for Style), Z (for classifieds) becomes 1, 2, 3, 4, 5.
                  Sequences are issue-specific. If the next day's issue omits S, then the sequence
                  is 1, 2, 3, 4. </comment>
               <comment>A block number is applied to newspapers that organize different articles
                  according to contiguous blocks on the page. Blocks are often rectangular, but they
                  may take other shapes. Blocks are numbered according to the expected
                  directionality of the script. If the language is written primarily left-to-right
                  then top-to-bottom (e.g., English), blocks are numbered according to the position
                  of the top-leftmost corner of the block relative to the page. If the newspaper
                  does not have a primary script directionality, but a mix of them, it cannot be
                  given an WF URI. </comment>
            </ref-system>
            <ref-system WF-supported="false" type="material">
               <step>date</step>
               <step optional="true">section</step>
               <step>page</step>
               <step>block</step>
               <step>column</step>
               <step type="implicit">line</step>
               <comment>This system is not WF supported, because it anticipates that, instead of an
                  integer, an ISO-compliant date be provided. That kind of approach is feasible, but
                  requires some deliberation. At present, if a newspaper does not have volume/issue
                  numbers, only dates, then the base scriptum URI must point specifically to the
                  issue in question, not the newspaper as a whole. </comment>
            </ref-system>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>
      
      <scriptum-type xml:id="e-comm">
         <name>electronic communication</name>
         <wf-support>none</wf-support>
         <desc>Includes email, text messages. Generally speaking, this type of scriptum must be
            first rendered in another form before it is a candidate for WF URIs, because they lack
            any kind of explicit reference system. They are better handled by other fragment
            identification systems. </desc>
      </scriptum-type>

      <scriptum-type xml:id="database">
         <name>database</name>
         <wf-support>none</wf-support>
         <desc>Databases should provide their own method for identifying fragments.</desc>
      </scriptum-type>

      <scriptum-type xml:id="web-item">
         <name>web item</name>
         <wf-support>poor</wf-support>
         <desc>Covers blog posts, comments, anything that has its origin as an HTML document on the
            World Wide Web. Generally speaking, this type of scriptum must be first rendered in
            another form before it is a candidate for WF URIs, because they lack any kind of
            explicit reference system. They are better handled by other fragment identification
            systems, e.g., XPointer. An exception is made for scholarly articles in HTML that have
            been provided paragraph numeration. </desc>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <!-- Not sure if the URL itsewf suffices, or more attention needs to be given to this aspect. -->
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <ref-systems>
            <ref-system type="logical">
               <step>paragraph</step>
               <comment>The paragraphs must be explicitly labeled in a system convertible to
                  integers.</comment>
            </ref-system>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>
      
      <scriptum-type xml:id="manuscript">
         <name>manuscript</name>
         <wf-support>mixed</wf-support>
         <desc>A hand-written document made of parchment (vellum) or paper. Although a very
            common type of scriptum from the ancient and medieval world, items are still handwritten
            today. The examples below presume ancient and medieval manuscripts, many of which are
            objects of institutional preservation and cataloguing. </desc>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <base-uri-source></base-uri-source>
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <ref-systems>
            <ref-system type="material">
               <step>folio</step>
               <step>side</step>
               <step optional="true">column</step>
               <step>line</step>
               <comment>This system relies upon the assumption that folios are uniquely numbered.
                  Many manuscripts have two or more series of folio numbers inscribed, reflecting
                  different numeration systems applied at different times. Those manuscripts can be
                  the target of a scriptum URI, but not of a reference URI. An WF URI pointing to
                  such manuscripts in the base URI must point in the reference URI to a scriptum
                  that is either a facsimile of the manuscript with clear folio labeling, or a
                  catalog that provides a unique reference system for the manuscript. In the case of
                  the latter, labeling will be partial, focusing on the starts of individual works
                  within the manuscript. Those who apply catalog numeration to a manuscript must
                  take care to ensure they have (1) identified the correct manuscript entry in the
                  catalog, and (2) ensured that folio numeration is consistent and complete. If
                  either condition fails to hold, the catalog should not be used as a reference
                  authority for that manuscript.</comment>
            </ref-system>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>
      
      <scriptum-type xml:id="book">
         <name>book</name>
         <wf-support>good</wf-support>
         <desc>Covers a variety of scripta, but excludes any other scriptum types that are special
            forms of books (e.g., manuscripts). In these examples, the term entails texts
            mechanically printed on paper, joined together in a case, binding, or both. </desc>
         <base-uri-source-suggestions>
            <base-uri-source></base-uri-source>
         </base-uri-source-suggestions>
         <ref-systems>
            <ref-system>
               <step optional="true" repeatable="true">volume</step>
               <step>page</step>
               <step optional="true">note</step>
               <step>line</step>
            </ref-system>
         </ref-systems>
      </scriptum-type>

   </scriptum-types>

   <work-types>
      <!-- This is not an exhaustive list of work types, only a diagnostic sample, to illustrate WF URI coverage -->
      <work-type xml:id="prose">
         <name>prose</name>
         <desc>Covers a great deal of declarative and descriptive writing, both fictious and
            non-fictious, typically printed with numbered volumes, pages. Line numbers are implied.
            Note numbers are common in non-fiction, particularly scholarly communication. Some prose
            that becomes a special object of editorial attention may acquire two or more sets of standard
            reference systems reflecting the editorial and publishing tradition.</desc>
         <scriptum-type>journal</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>newspaper</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>book</scriptum-type>
      </work-type>
      
      <work-type xml:id="scripture">
         <name>scripture</name>
         <desc>Text authoritative in a religious tradition. Reference systems tend to begin with a
            unit frequently smaller than a sentence. In Jewish and Christian Scriptures these are termed verses; in Islamic, ayahs.
            These are then grouped in larger structures, as chapters or surahs. Grouping can also occur in some larger numbered units (e.g.,
            kathismata in the Greek Psalter) before the book level is reached. If the books are commonly numbered (e.g., Qur'anic suras),
            then they will be part of an WF reference system. Otherwise, a URI for the book/work must be supplied in the base URI.
            At times this may pose a problem for determining a URI. For example, there is a dbpedia entry for the books of Samuel, but not one
            for either of the two books separately.
         </desc>
         <scriptum-type>journal</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>newspaper</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>papyrus</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>ostracon</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>manuscript</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>book</scriptum-type>
      </work-type>
      <work-type xml:id="poem">
         <name>poem</name>
         <desc>A form of literature that uses aesthetic and often rhythmic qualities of language to evoke
         greater meaning. Reference systems tend to build up from line number, to stanzas, odes, and many
         other types of larger structures, which vary from work to work and cannot be predicted. </desc>
         <scriptum-type>journal</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>newspaper</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>papyrus</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>ostracon</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>manuscript</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>book</scriptum-type>
      </work-type>
      <work-type xml:id="play">
         <name>play</name>
         <desc>A form of literature that consists of speech and actions intended to be performed by
            one or more persons. Many plays frequently have a built in logical reference system
            keyed to acts, scenes, lines. The expected structure differs according to era, language,
            and work. A number of plays without such a clear logical structure can be referred to by
            material features of the underlying scriptum.
         </desc>
         <scriptum-type>journal</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>newspaper</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>papyrus</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>ostracon</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>manuscript</scriptum-type>
         <scriptum-type>book</scriptum-type>
      </work-type>
      <work-type xml:id="bill">
         <name>bill</name>
         <desc>A piece of legislation</desc>
      </work-type>
   </work-types>

   <!-- Here are the examples. -->

   
   <wf-example xml:id="e001a">
      <wf-uri>http://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.oxy;41;2950#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>https://papyri.info/ddbdp/chla;47;1414#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>https://www.trismegistos.org/text/16514#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <scriptum-type>papyrus</scriptum-type>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to line 1 of a dedication to Diocletian and Maximian, qua scriptum. The papyrus
         itsewf can be the reference scriptum because the lines lend themselves to implicit
         numbering. One doesn't need the latest modern publication of this papyrus as a reference
         scriptum, but that wouldn't be wrong. One point of unclarity: is a name for the papyrus,
         but what would be the name for the 1972 publication of this papyrus? It can't be
         http://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.oxy;41;2950 otherwise you have a case of a URI naming two
         different things which is a foundational no-no. The same is true for the ChLA reference.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e001b">
      <wf-uri>http://papyri.info/ddbdp/p.oxy;41;2950#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1::Val[1]$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>https://papyri.info/ddbdp/chla;47;1414#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1::Val[1]$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>https://www.trismegistos.org/text/16514#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1::Val[1]$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <scriptum-type>papyrus</scriptum-type>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Similar to #e001a, except it points to the first token "Val". Note, the base URI points
         to the papyrus as scriptum, and so expects tokenization to be based upon what is there, not
         in the restored reading. For that, see #e001c. The challenge is defining a mechanism for EpiDoc
         TEI XML that allows a processor to tokenize based only on what is seen in the scriptum, not what
         is in the edition.
      </desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e001c">
      <wf-uri>https://lccn.loc.gov/01005637#$wf0:a=s;t=l;r=.;41:2950:1::Val(erio)[1]$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>http://id.lib.harvard.edu/alma/990001053470203941/catalog#$wf0:a=s;t=l;r=.;47:1414:1::Val(erio)[1]$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>false</optimal>
      <scriptum-type>book</scriptum-type>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Similar to #e001b, except it points to the first token "Val(erio)" in modern editions of
         the papyrus. Note, the base URI points to the editions (Oxyrhynchus papyri in the first
         option and Chartae Latinae antiquiores in the second) as scriptum, and so expects
         tokenization to be based upon what is there, not in the original papyrus. For that, see
         #e001b. Note that papyri.info URIs have been avoided, because they appear to be names only
         for the original papyrus, not for any particular edition. The first option's base URI comes
         from the Library of Congress and the second from Harvard's online catolog system. This illustrates
         the many options available to someone who is finding scriptum URIs. Note that because each base URI
         points to a series in its entirety, the reference system begins with volume then item number. Both are
         logical reference systems, in that the item number might span pages, or share a page with other items.
         Strictly speaking, the last reference, to line one, is a material unit, not logical. But because the
         primary division type is logical the system as a whole is logical. A reference system such as this might include
         a mix of material and logical units. That would be a problem if the lines were not explicitly numbered,
         but they are in these editions.
      </desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e002a">
      <wf-uri>http://papyri.info/apis/columbia.apis.3099#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <scriptum-type>ostracon</scriptum-type>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to line 1 of an ostracon, O.Col.inv. 3099 (acc. MMA 14.1.199?). Note that
      the token assumes text from the object itsewf, not a modern publication.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e003a">
      <wf-uri>http://www.trismegistos.org/text/156749#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;1::Imp[1]$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <scriptum-type>inscription</scriptum-type>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to line 1 of an inscription on a milestone of Diocletian and Maximian, found in Britain. Note that
      the token assumes text from the object itsewf, not a modern publication.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e004a">
      <wf-uri>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/860129739#$wf0:a=w;t=m;r=.;14.2$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to page 14, line 2 of Burkert's Lore qua work. In other words, this URI points
      to any version of Burkert's work.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e004b">
      <wf-uri>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/860129739#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;14.2$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to page 14, line 2 of Burkert's Lore qua scriptum. In other words, this URI points
      only to this edition of Burkert's work, and is not concerned with the work as such.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e005a">
      <wf-uri>https://doi.org/10.1075/target.26.3.02zuf#$wf0:a=w;t=m;r=.;361$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to the first page of Sadrine Zufferey and Bruno Cartoni, "A Multifactorial
         Analysis of Explicitation in Translation," Target: International Journal of Translation
         Studies 26.3 (2014): 361-384. </desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e006a">
      <wf-uri>urn:issn:2325-9345#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;68:387-68:404$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>urn:issn:2325-9345#$wf0:a=w;t=m;r=.;68:387-68:404$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>false</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to Dumbarton Oaks Papers, vol. 68, pages 145-179, corresponding to the article
         Çağaptay, Suna. “Results of the Tophane Area GPR Surveys, Bursa, Turkey.” Dumbarton Oaks
         Papers 68 (2014): 387–404. This URI intends to point to the entire article either as a
         scriptum or as a work, but there is no DOI assigned to it. One could refer to the journal
         as a work in its own right, or a scriptum, hence the two possibilities. If there existed a
         fragid structure for works, the second item could possibly be narrowed down within the base
         URI and its fragment.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e006b">
      <wf-uri>urn:issn:2325-9345#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;68:387:2:17-68:387:2:20&amp;68:387:n4$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>urn:issn:2325-9345#$wf0:a=w;t=m;r=.;68:387:2:17-68:387:2:20&amp;68:387:n4$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>urn:issn:2325-9345#$wf0:a=s;t=m;r=.;68:387:2:17-68:387:2:20::evidence[1]&amp;68:387:n4$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>false</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Refers to Dumbarton Oaks Papers, vol. 68, page 387, corresponding to the article
         Çağaptay, Suna. “Results of the Tophane Area GPR Surveys, Bursa, Turkey,” specifically page
         387, column 2, lines 17-20, as well as note 4. The third URI option specifies the actual text
         (and therefore can be applied only to to the base URI qua scriptum, not qua work). This
         example demonstrates how to build an WF URI that pinpoint where one scriptum quotes from
         another (here p. 75 from a book section written by Colin Imber).</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e007a">
      <wf-uri>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Categories_(Aristotle)#$wf0:a=w;t=m;r=urn:isbn:9782251004976;1:1:21$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>false</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Refers to Aristotle's Categories, indicating use of the so-called Bekker line number
         system. But the reference scriptum is Bodëús's 2002 edition, which has differences, small
         and large, with Bekker's and Minio-Paluello's editions, which most people treat as if the
         same system. But they aren't. In WF-conformant media, one should not treat the URIs of
         those editions as being synonymous. No creator of WF-conformant media MUST support every
         reference system for a given text. But if someone did wish to support all three editions'
         approach to reference systems based on "Bekker" numbers, that person would need to take
         advantage of whatever mechanisms are allowed or advised in the target media format to
         provide alternative reference systems. Anyone writing an WF processor may wish to build a
         messaging system notifying users when an WF URI matchs a file in every parameter except the
         reference scriptum. </desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e007b">
      <wf-uri>urn:isbn:9782251004976#$wf0:a=s;w=http://dbpedia.org/resource/Categories_(Aristotle);t=m;r=.;1:1:21::ἐν[1]$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>http://lccn.loc.gov/50036648#$wf0:a=s;w=http://dbpedia.org/resource/Categories_(Aristotle);t=m;r=.;1:1:20::ἐν[1]$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>urn:isbn:9782251004976#$wf0:a=s;w=http://dbpedia.org/resource/Categories_(Aristotle);t=m;r=http://lccn.loc.gov/50036648;1:1:20::ἐν[1]$</wf-uri>
      <wf-uri>http://lccn.loc.gov/50036648#$wf0:a=s;w=http://dbpedia.org/resource/Categories_(Aristotle);t=m;r=urn:isbn:9782251004976;1:1:21::ἐν[1]$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>false</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>All four URIs are constrained scriptum URIs that point to the same word, ἐν. The first
         and third are about the edition published by Bodëús; the second and third, that published
         by Minio-Paluello. The first and second point to the base URI scriptum itself as the basis
         for the material reference system. Note, in the third and fourth examples, each URI indicates that the
         base URI is one scriptum but the reference scriptum is the other. The lineation must correspond to
         what is in the reference scriptum. In this case, the word ἐν appears on two different lines.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e008a">
      <wf-uri>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Iliad#$wf0:a=w;t=l;r=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/968653045;1:1$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>poem</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>logical</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to book 1, line 1 of the Iliad, as numbered by West's edition. A large number of scripta could
      have been used for the reference system. It would be valid but inappropriate to point to the work URI as 
      the basis for the reference system, because it points exclusively to a concept, not a material object, and
      cannot point to a single object.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e008b">
      <wf-uri>http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/968653045#$wf0:a=w;w=http://dbpedia.org/resource/Iliad;t=l;r=.;1:1$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>poem</work-type>
      <scriptum-type>book</scriptum-type>
      <ref-system-type>material</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to West's edition, constrained to Iliad, (logical) line 1.1. One could point to the material
      reference system, but that seems unnecessarily obscure. Most target data will be built upon the logical
      reference system.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e009a">
      <wf-uri>http://digitalhumanities.org/dhq/vol/14/3/000484/000484.html#p5$wf0:a=s;t=l;r=.;::HSS[1]$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>prose</work-type>
      <scriptum-type>web-item</scriptum-type>
      <ref-system-type>logical</ref-system-type>
      <desc>The base URI points to Christine Barats, Valérie Schafer, Andreas Fickers, "Fading
         Away... The challenge of sustainability in digital studies," Digital Humanities Quarterly
         14.3 (2020). In this case, the base URI (with fragment) is enough for most purposes. But an WF URI can
      be employed to point to a specific text fragment, here rendered without any reference steps.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
   <wf-example xml:id="e010a">
      <wf-uri>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Psalms#$wf0:a=w;t=l;r=http://id.lib.harvard.edu/aleph/012287584/catalog;$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>poem</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>logical</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to Psalm 30.1, English numeration system, via the Hollis URI for the Francis
         Parris 1760 edition of the King James Version of the Bible. For alternative versification
         systems see #e010b and #e010c.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e010b">
      <wf-uri>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Psalms#$wf0:a=w;t=l;r=urn:isbn:3438052199;$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>poem</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>logical</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to Psalm 30.1, Hebrew numeration system, via the URN pointing to the Biblia
         Hebraica Stuttgartensia. For alternative versification systems see #e010a and
         #e010c.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   <wf-example xml:id="e010c">
      <wf-uri>http://dbpedia.org/resource/Psalms#$wf0:a=w;t=l;r=http://www.worldcat.org/oclc/19565412;$</wf-uri>
      <optimal>true</optimal>
      <work-type>poem</work-type>
      <ref-system-type>logical</ref-system-type>
      <desc>Points to Psalm 30.1, Septuagint numeration system, via the Worldcat URI for Rahwfs's edition of the 
         Greek Septuagint. For alternative versification
         systems see #e010a and #e010b.</desc>
   </wf-example>
   
</wf-examples>
